Guide to the Selected Polish Falcons and Polish National Alliance Organizations in Braddock, Pa. Records, 1899-1967 AIS.1979.13
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Selected Polish Falcons and Polish National Alliance Organizations in Braddock, Pa. Records
1956-1959
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Polish Falcons of America. Nest 821 (Braddock, Pa.)
Polish Falcons of America. Nest 490 (Braddock, Pa.)
Polish Falcons of America. Nest 15 (Braddock, Pa.)
AIS.1979.13
17.5 Linear Feet (14 boxes)
This collection consists of the records of Polish Falcons Nests and Polish National Alliance Groups in Braddock, PA, 1899-1967. The collection is organized into four series including records of Polish Falcons, Nest 15, 1907-1967; Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, 1899-1961; and Polish Falcons Nest 821, 1907-1917.
History
The Polish National Alliance (PNA or the Alliance) is a non-profit, ethnically-based fraternal insurance benefit society. The PNA was founded on February 15, 1880, in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania and based on the purchase of life insurance and benefits include a variety of sports, youth and culture programs, and a college scholarship program.
The Polish Falcons of America, a fraternal benefit society and physical fitness organization, is a direct outgrowth of a similar organization that was organized in Poland in 1867. The first Nest, or lodge, in the United States was established on June 12, 1887, in Chicago, Illinois. In 1928, the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania granted the Polish Falcons of America a charter to sell life insurance. The organization is now domiciled in Green Tree Borough, a suburb of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Polish Falcons of America currently holds licenses to sell insurance in the states of Pennsylvania, New York, Illinois, Connecticut, Indiana, New Jersey, Massachusetts, Michigan, and Wisconsin.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection consists of records of Polish Falcons Nests and Polish National Alliance Groups in Braddock, PA, 1899-1967. The collection is organized into four series. Series I. consists of records of Polish Falcons, Nest 15, 1907-1967. The records consist of financial records, dues books, visitor registration books, and other record books. Series II. consists of records of Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, 1899-1961. The records constist of receipt books, 1901-1929; dues books, 1899-1924; record books, 1899-1959; financial records, 1956-1959; combined dues books, 1912-1936; and combined library records, 1907-1961.
Series III. consists of the combined receipt books of Polish Falcons Nests 15 and 490, 1917-1948. Series IV. consists of dues books of Polish Falcons Nest 821, 1907-1917. The records and reports include member name, type of plan, premium, and amounts given and received. The records are arranged by year.
Note: Most records are in Polish
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Polish National Alliance Group 490, Braddock, Pa., June 6, 1979.
Previous Citation
Selected Polish Falcons and Polish National Alliance Groups in Braddock, Pa. Records, 1899-1967, AIS.1979.13, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Polish National Alliance Group 490, Records, 1956-1959, AIS 73:13b, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh.
Societies; Fraternal organizations -- Pennsylvania -- Braddock; Ethnic groups; Polish Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Braddock -- Societies and clubs; Polish Falcons of America. Nest 15 (Braddock, Pa.); Polish Falcons of America. Nest 490 (Braddock, Pa.); Polish Falcons of America. Nest 821 (Braddock, Pa.); Polish National Alliance of the United States of North America. Group 490 (Braddock, Pa.)
- Polish Falcons, Nest 15, 1907-1967; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I consists of membership applications, rate books, dues books, financial records, and record books of Polish Falcons, Nest 15.
  - Membership Applications, 1914 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Rate Book for Juvenile Department, 1954 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Monthly Financial Report, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tax Returns, 1919, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dues Book, 1955-1967 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Sokol Polski, 1937-1948 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Record Book, 1907-1916 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Sheet Music, no date (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Visitor Registers, 1949-1952 (Oversize 1-2)
  - Oversize Material (Map-case 7-4)
    - Picture of the Staff of the Consulate of Poland, 1933-1934; 1.
    - Picture of the Braddock Falcons baseball team, 1922-1923; 2.
    - Picture of the Braddock Falcons gym class, 1928; 3.
    - Picture of 50th anniversary of Polish Falcons, 1930; 4.
    - Picture of Polish Falcons Training Class, 5.
    - Picture, Training Class, 6.
    - Poster of Yozef Pilsudski, 7.
- Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, 1899-1961; II.
  Series II consists of receipt books, dues books, combined library records, record books, a photo, prints, and posters of the Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490.
  - Receipt Books, 1901-1919 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Receipt Books, 1906-1919 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Receipt Books, 1907-1921 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Receipt Books, 1919-1925 (Box 2, Volume 4)
  - Receipt Books, 1920-1923 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Receipt Books, 1924-1925 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Receipt Books, 1926-1929 (Box 3, Volume 3)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 821, Receipt Book, no date (Box 3, Volume 4)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 793, Dues Book, 1906-1913 (Box 3, Volume 5)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, Dues Books, 1899 (Box 4, Volume 1)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, Dues Books, 1901-1903 (Box 4, Volume 2)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, Dues Books, 1904-1905 (Box 4, Volume 3)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, Dues Books, 1904-1909 (Box 4, Volume 4)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, Dues Books, 1907-1911 (Box 5, Volume 1)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, Dues Books, 1910-1912 (Box 5, Volume 2)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, Dues Books, 1913-1917 (Box 5, Volume 3)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, Dues Books, 1913-1917 (Box 6, Volume 1)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, Dues Books, 1914-1917 (Box 6, Volume 2)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, Dues Books, 1915-1916 (Box 6, Volume 3)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, Dues Books, 1918-1919 (Box 7, Volume 1-2)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, Dues Books, 1920-1921 (Box 7, Volume 3)
  - Polish National Alliance, Group 490 and Polish Falcons, Nest 490, Dues Books, 1920-1924 (Box 8, Volume 1)
  - Combined Dues Book, 1912-1915 (Box 8, Volume 2)
  - Combined Dues Book, 1934-1936 (Box 8, Volume 3)
  - Combined Dues Book, no date (Box 8, Volume 4)
  - Combined Library Records, 1907-1961 (Box 8, Volume 5-6)
  - Record Book, 1899-1907 (Box 9, Volume 1)
  - Record Book, 1905-1917 (Box 9, Volume 2)
  - Record Book, 1909-1918 (Box 9, Volume 3)
  - Record Book, 1917-1925 (Box 9, Volume 4)
  - Record Book, 1921-1929 (Box 10, Volume 1)
  - Record Book, 1930-1939 (Box 10, Volume 2)
  - Record Book, 1940-1946 (Box 10, Volume 3)
  - Record Book, 1953-1959 (Box 10, Volume 4)
  - Membership Applications, no date (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Monthly Financial Reports, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Monthly Financial Reports, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Monthly Financial Reports, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Monthly Financial Reports, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Records, no date (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Oversize Material (Map-case 8-10, Folder 11)
    - Group Photo - Dom Sokoli Gwiazda #15, no date; 1.
    - Print of Painting - Heroic Death of Casimir Pulaski by S. Bartowski, 1933; 2.
    - Poster - Tryptyk Grunwaldzki, 1410-1910, no date; 3.
- Polish Falcons, Nest 15 and Nest 490, Combined Receipt Books, 1917-1948; III.
  Series III includes combined receipt books for Polish Falcons Nests 25 and 490.
  - 1917-1919 (Box 12, Volume 1)
  - 1920-1925 (Box 12, Volume 2)
  - 1925-1930 (Box 12, Volume 3)
  - 1931-1935 (Box 13, Volume 1)
  - 1936-1942 (Box 13, Volume 2)
  - 1943-1948 (Box 13, Volume 3)
- Polish Falcons, Nest 821, Dues Books, 1907-1917; IV.
  Series IV includes Dues Books for Polish Falcons, Nest 821.
  - 1907-1909 (Box 14, Volume 1)
  - 1908-1909 (Box 14, Volume 2)
  - 1914-1915 (Box 14, Volume 3)
  - 1916-1917 (Box 14, Volume 4)